Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives audio tapes collection, 1980s-1990s.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives audio tapes collection, 1980s-1990s.
SJA 009
1.5 linear feet
The Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives audio tapes collection consists of audio cassette tapes which contain either interviews or lectures which are relevant to the history of Jews who settled in the American Southwest or to more general Jewish topics.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of audio cassette tapes which contain either interviews or lectures which are relevant to the history of Jews who settled in the American Southwest or to more general Jewish topics. The bulk of the tapes consists either of interviews with the descendants of pioneer Jewish families in this region or are recordings of accounts of prejudice (especially anti-Semitism) or intolerance which were given at the Anne Frank Exhibit's tolerance talks at Tucson's Jewish Community Center in September of 1995. Major topics of the testimonies given include prejudice against Jews, blacks, and homosexuals.
There are also two tapes with recordings of Sephardic songs and prayers in this collection.
47 taped programs (some programs consist of more than one cassette).
The audio tapes have been arranged alphabetically according to the name of the recorded speaker or the subject of the discussion or lecture. Tapes should be requested by number.
Capin family.; Gustoff family.; Singer, Isaac Bashevis, 1904-.; Antisemitism -- United States.; Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.).; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945).; Jewish newspapers -- Arizona -- Tucson.; Jews -- Arizona.; Jews -- New Mexico.; Jews -- Persecutions.; Jews -- Southwest, New -- History.; Jews -- West (U.S.).; Marranos.; Sephardim -- History.; Sephardim -- Music.; West (U.S.) -- Ethnic relations.; West (U.S.) -- History.; Audio Tapes.
Container List
- Achley, Guy; Bremer, Fred, 1995. (Box 1, Tape 1)
  A: Testimony of Guy Achley at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Fred Bremer at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, 1991. (Box 1, Tape 2 A)
  Opening program at the dedication of the archives. Speakers include Abraham Chanin, Floyd Fierman, Harriet Rochlin, Fred Rochlin.
- Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, 1991. (Box 1, Tape 2 B)
- Breger, Bertha, 1991. (Box 1, Tape 3)
  Talk by Bertha Breger in which she discusses the history of Jews in Tucson.
- Brooks, Benjamin (Tucson), 1987. (Box 1, Tape 4)
  Interview by Dave Laughlin (?) with Benjamin Brooks concerning the "Arizona Post."
- Capin, Zellie, 1997. (Box 1, Tape 5)
  Interview by Melissa Amado with Zellie Capin concerning the Capin family and its many business dealings.
- Cargas, Harry James, 1995. (Box 1, Tape 6)
  A: Performance by members of the Grace St. Paul Church of Cargas's musical "I Never Saw Another Butterfly."
  B: Lecture on the Holocaust given by Cargas at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Chanin, Abraham, 1990. (Box 1, Tape 7)
  Chanin discusses the Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives and a conference on the "hidden Jews" of the Southwest on a radio broadcast.
- Chanin, Abraham, ca. 1990. (Box 1, Tape 8 A)
  Lectures entitled "From Spain to the Southwest" given by Chanin.
- Chanin, Abraham, ca. 1990. (Box 1, Tape 8 B)
- Classen, Susan; Tang, Esther, 1995. (Box 1, Tape 9)
  A: Testimony of Susan Classen at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Esther Tang at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Cohen, Judith (Box 1, Tape 10)
  Compilation of Sephardic songs by Judith Cohen under the title "Primavera en Salonica."
- Danoff, Izzy, (Tucson), 1988. (Box 1, Tape 11)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Izzy Danoff concerning his family’s migration to New Mexico and Arizona as homesteaders.
- Duckstein, Lucien; Tucson Police Department, 1995. (Box 1, Tape 12)
  A: Testimony of Lucien Duckstein at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Presentation by the Tucson Police Department entitled "Voice of Hate."
- Gold, Sylvia Lehman (Sun City, AZ) [poor sound quality], 1987. (Box 1, Tape 13)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Sylvia Lehman Gold.
- Goldbaum, Emma V. (Tucson), 1990. (Box 1, Tape 14)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Emma V. Goldbaum concerning her family's history.
- Grant, Lillian Lopez; Levkowitz, Bertie, 1995. (Box 1, Tape 15)
  A: Testimony of Lillian Lopez at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Bertie Levkowitz at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Gustoff family (Box 1, Tape 16)
  Lecture on the Gustoff family of Taos, New Mexico, by Susan Campbell.
- Hargrove, Jesse; Kozolchyk, Billie, 1995. (Box 2, Tape 17)
  A: Public service announcement given in Spanish by Billie Kozolchyk.
  B: Testimony of Jesse Hargrove at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Hernandez, Francis, 1991 (?). (Box 2, Tape 18)
  Hernandez speaks at the Society for the Study of Hidden Jews in Taos, New Mexico.
- Hernandez, Mona; Trujillo, Gloria, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 19)
  Interview with Mona Hernandez and Gloria Trujillo in Fort Burguin, New Mexico.
- Hispanic Center director (Box 2, Tape 20)
  Lecture by the director of the Hispanic Center (at New Mexico State University?) in which he discusses the possibility that there are Chicano people of [crypto-] Jewish heritage, and what the implications of that would be.
- "International Conference on the Inquisition in the Americas and the Hidden Jews of the Southwest," Held at the Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 21)
  A: Lecture by Dr. Abraham Peck of the American Jewish Archives.
  B: Lecture by Rabbi Jacob Ott.
- Jensen, Henning; Senor, Irving, 1995. (Box 2, Tape 22)
  A: Lecture by Henning Jensen entitled "Choice to Be Moral: The Danish Experience" at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Irving Senor at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Kozolchyk, Billie; the "Third Street Kids," 1995. (Box 2, Tape 23)
  A: The "Third Street Kids" of the Children's Theater put on a performance entitled "What the Heck is Normal?" at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Billie Kozolchyk at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Kozolchyk, Shaun, 1995. (Box 2, Tape 24)
  Testimony of Shaun Kozolchyk at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions in which she describes her participation in the "March of the Living" program of Jewish youth who journey to Poland.
- Krupp, Alvin and Janet (Safford, AZ), 1991. (Box 2, Tape 25)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Alvin and Janet Krupp concerning his family's migration from Lithuania to El Paso and their subsequent settlement in Safford, Arizona.
- Las Cruces, New Mexico's Jewish History, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 26 A)
  History of the Jews of Las Cruces, New Mexico as presented by the New Mexico Jewish Historical Society.
- Las Cruces, New Mexico's Jewish History, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 26 B)
- Las Cruces, New Mexico's Jewish History, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 26 C)
- Las Cruces, New Mexico's Jewish History, 1991. (Box 2, Tape 26 D)
- Lehman, Carl (Sun City, AZ), 1990. (Box 2, Tape 27)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Carl Lehman concerning his family's migration from Germany to New Mexico, via Safford, Arizona.
- Levenson, Sherman and Fanny, 1987. (Box 2, Tape 28 A)
  Interview with Sherman and Fanny Levenson in which they describe the history of the Jews of La Mesa, New Mexico.
- Levenson, Sherman and Fanny, 1987. (Box 2, Tape 28 B)
- Levy, Esther Farber, 1987. (Box 2, Tape 29)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Esther Farber Levy concerning family history.
- Lewkowitz, Herman, 1990. (Box 2, Tape 30)
  Interview with Jerry Lewkowitz in which he discusses the life of his father, Herman Lewkowitz.
- Lisitsky, Charles, 1988. (Box 3, Tape 31)
  Interview by Abe Chanin with Charles Lisitsky concerning the history of his family's stores in Arizona.
- Marshall, Jonathan, 1990. (Box 3, Tape 32)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Jonathan Marshall concerning family history. His grandfather (?) was Louis Marshall, U.S. lawyer and president of the American Jewish Committee.
- Mechles, Leon, 1993. (Box 3, Tape 33)
  Interview by Tim Boling with Leon Mechles concerning the Holocaust.
- Melczer, Mrs. Ed, 1989. (Box 3, Tape 34)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Mrs. Ed Melczer concerning family history (especially in Nogales, Arizona).
- Mills, Cliff (Box 3, Tape 35)
  Interview with Cliff Mills in which he describes the history of the Jews of Taos, New Mexico, at the turn of the century.
- New Mexico's "Hidden Jews," 1988. (Box 3, Tape 36)
  National Public Radio program on New Mexico's so-called "hidden Jews."
- Oberman, Heiko; Chanin, Abraham (Box 3, Tape 37)
  A: Lecture by Heiko Oberman entitled "The Roots of Anti-Semitism."
  B: Lecture by Abraham Chanin entitled "Jewish Roots of the University of Arizona."
- Pakier, Freddi; Oberman, Heiko, 1995. (Box 3, Tape 38 A)
  A: Testimony of Freddi Pakier at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Lecture (Part 1) by Heiko Oberman entitled "Witness to Persecution and Survival" given at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Oberman, Heiko; Fortune, E. Anne, 1995. (Box 3, Tape 38 B)
  A: Lecture (Part 2) by Heiko Oberman entitled "Witness to Persecution and Survival" given at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of E. Anne Fortune at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Resnick, Ed (Phoenix), 1990. (Box 3, Tape 39)
  Interview by Abe Chanin (?) with Ed Resnick concerning family history.
- Rutz, Rebecca, 1987. (Box 3, Tape 40)
  Interview by Dave Laughlin (?) with Rebecca Rutz concerning the "Arizona Post."
- Sephardic songs and prayers, 1992. (Box 3, Tape 41)
  Compilation of Sephardic songs and prayers distributed in commemoration of the 500th anniversary of the Jews' expulsion from Spain.
- Singer, Isaac Bashevis (Tucson) (Box 3, Tape 42 A)
  Interview with Isaac Bashevis Singer in which he discusses his life and work.
- Singer, Isaac Bashevis (Tucson) (Box 3, Tape 42 B)
- Solomon / Lesinsky family (Box 3, Tape 43)
  Readings from articles related to the Solomon / Lesinsky family of Clifton, Arizona.
- Stern, Eugene (Albuquerque) (Box 3, Tape 44)
  Interview with Charna Stern in which she talks about her father, Eugene Stern.
- Strong, Douglas Morgan; Clarke, Ray, 1995. (Box 3, Tape 45)
  A: Testimony of the Rev. Douglas Morgan Strong at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
  B: Testimony of Ray Clarke at the Anne Frank tolerance discussions.
- Williams, Frances; Stern, Charna, 1998. (Box 3, Tape 46)
  Interview with Francis Williams and Charna Stern in which they discuss the history of the Jews of Las Cruces, New Mexico.
- Zuckerman, La Dell (Las Cruces, NM), 1991. (Box 4, Tape 47)
  Interview by Abe Chanin with La Dell Zuckerman concerning family history in Las Cruces, New Mexico.
- Drachman, Roy, 1996 March 19 (Box 4, Tape 48)
- Stern, Eugene (Albuquerque); Williams, Frances; Stern, Charna; Zuckerman, La Dell; Access Compact Disc 1988, 1991 (Box 4, Tape 49)
  Audio Compact Disc that contains MP3 files of tape 44, tape 46, tape 47